A Guide to the Boy Scout Troop 1168 Records, 1965-1980
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Boy Scout Troop 1168 Records 1965-1980
Thomas Balch Library
M 082, VC 0052, OMB 015
This collection contains the administrative records of Boy Scout Troop 1168. Included are troop rosters, record books, charters, applications for merit badges and advancement, as well information about camps. Photographs document activities of the troop, including Camps Goshen and Marriott, Swim-o-rees, and Hike-o-rees. There are 114 photographs in a wide variety of sizes. The large format photographs are housed in a folder with the manuscript collection. Other, small format, photographs are sleeved and housed in a separate box. There are four banners, three of which are made of tanned animal hides, a plaque from Camp Marriott, and three trophies. There is also a folder of material about Willie Davis, a committee chairman of Troop 1168. Davis died in 1970 and the troop named its meeting room in his honor.
James P. Roberts, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research. One folder restricted until 1 January 2052. "Applications to Become a Scout" and "Scout Medical and Health Records" contain privacy protected information such as health histories and medical information. Access to these records by the general public is restricted for 72 years after the creation of the records. Until 1 January 2052, access to one folder in this collection is limited to the subject of the record (the scout); the duly qualified conservator or guardian of the subject of the record; the next-of-kin, if the scout is deceased (The next of kin may be the following: surviving spouse that has not remarried; father, mother, son, daughter, sister, or brother); the duly qualified executor or administrator of the estate of the subject of the record; an attorney, attorney-in-fact, or other agent or representative of any of the persons described above, acting pursuant to a written power-of-attorney or other written authorization; or a duly authorized representative of an agency or instrumentality of federal, state, or local government seeking the record in the ordinary course of performing its official duties.
Acquisition Information
James P. Roberts, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2012.0058
Historical Information
The Boy Scouts of America (BSA) incorporated in 1910 and was modeled on the British Boy Scout Association. There were several youth and scouting organizations operating in the first decade of the 20th century, including the Woodcraft Indians and the Sons of Daniel Boone, which merged with the BSA to form a dominant scouting group with an emphasis on camping, outdoor activities, and Native American lore.
For administrative purposes, the BSA is divided into geographic regions on the national level, and further subdivided into area councils, districts, and, finally, into troops. Each troop is individually chartered by the BSA with a sponsoring institution, often a church, fraternal lodge, or a parent-teacher association.
In 1960, James P. Roberts, a native of Loudoun County, founded Troop 1168 in Middleburg. The troop was part of the Blue Ridge District, which included both Loudoun and Fauquier Counties. Troop 1168 initially operated as a troop for African American boys. Integration had been a controversial subject in the BSA since its founding and decisions about it were not made at the national level, but were left to the individual troops. Troop approaches to integration, therefore, usually strongly resembled the approaches used by the communities in which they operated. Troops in the Northeast and on the West Coast began integrating much earlier than troops in parts of the Midwest and South, for instance. Troop 1168 had been an all-African American troop, but in 1967 Roberts decided to allow any boy who applied for membership to join, resulting in the first integrated BSA troop Loudoun County.
Troop 1168 still exists today. Because of reorganization of districts due to shifts and growth in the population of Northern Virginia, the troop is in the Goose Creek District.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the administrative records of Boy Scout Troop 1168. Included are troop rosters, record books, charters, applications for merit badges and advancement, as well information about camps. Photographs document activities of the troop, including Camps Goshen and Marriott, Swim-o-rees, and Hike-o-rees. There are 114 photographs in a wide variety of sizes. The large format photographs are housed in a folder with the manuscript collection. Other, small format, photographs are sleeved and housed in a separate box. There are four banners, three of which are made of tanned animal hides, a plaque from Camp Marriott, and three trophies. There is also a folder of material about Willie Davis, a committee chairman of Troop 1168. Davis died in 1970 and the troop named its meeting room in his honor.
Arrangement
Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"African Americans in the Boy Scout Movement." African American Registry, www.aaregistry.org/historic_events/view/african-american-boy-scout-movement (accessed 15 January 2013).
Boy Scouts of America, www.scouting.org (accessed 15 January 2013).
Boy Scout Troop 1168 Records, 1965-1980 (M 082), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
James P. Roberts Photograph Collection (VC 0019), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Leister, Harvey J. A History of Boy Scout Troops 161 in Fauquier County Virginia, 1938-2010. Warrenton, VA: Piedmont Press, 2010.
Robert, James P. Interview with Elizabeth E. Preston. 16 January 2013.
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - M 082
    - Advancement Reports, 1967-1972
    - Calendar, 1978-1979
    - Camp Marriott, 12-19 July 1969
    - Camp Rosters, n.d.
    - Charter Renewal Applications, 1966-1969
    - Goshen Scout Camps menus, c. 1970
    - Member Information Cards, 1965-1969
    - Membership Cards, 1979
    - Merit Badges: Applications, Advancement Reports, Certificates, Counselor Enrollment forms, 1968-1972
    - Newspaper Articles
    - Planning Minutes, 1965; 1972
    - Scouter Digest, 3 May 1971
    - Star Scout Scoreboard Cards (blank)
    - Troop Awards, 1965; 1970
    - Troop Charters: Middleburg, 1965-1979
    - Troop Charters: Rectortown (Troop 1172), 1971-1974
    - Troop Record Books, 1965; 1971; 1973
    - Troop Rosters, 1970-1980
    - RESTRICTED: "Applications to Become a Boy Scout" and "Scout Medical and Health Records"
      Baltimore, Shirley L.
      Basil, Everett Anthony
      Basil, James W.
      Basil, Levon
      Berryman, Roger L.
      Brooks, Lawrence
      Brown, Earl E.
      Dade, A. Calvin
      Dade, Theodore
      Fisher, Douglas
      Fisher, John M.
      Fisher, Michael A.
      Godray, Gulia W.
      Grayson, Rico M.
      Harris, Moses
      Howard, Austin E.
      Howard, Carter Nathanial
      Howard, William Gregory
      Hunter, Floyd Alvin
      Moore, Glandwood D. Jr.
      Moore, Wade Edward
      Richardson, James W.
      Robinson, Arthur Lloyd
      Robinson, Ray Anthony
      Shortridge, Ward
      Smith, Aaron Garcia
      Smith, Dana Franklin
      Smith, Wade
      Swann, William Jr.
      Thomas, Danny L.
      Washington, Glenn Ray
      Washington, Russell
      Woodson, Milton Wendell
      Young, William Thomas Sr. (Scoutmaster, Adult Medical and Health Record)
  - VC 0052
    - Large Photographs: vc_0052_98-103; vc_0052_105-110
    - Small photographs, 1965-1980
- (OMB 015)
  - (Box 1)
    - Banners
      - "Blackfoot Patrol," animal hide
      - "Fox Patrol," animal hide
      - "Staff Candles," animal hide
  - Troop 1168: Middleburg, VA Flag
  - Willie Davis material, 1970, 1972
  - (Box 2)
    - (Trophies)
      - Marriott 1971 Horseshoe Plaque
      - Middleburg VFD Best Appearing Boy Scout Troop, 1962
      - Swimoree [sic] 3rd Place, 1973
      - The Plains VFC 1st Prize Best Marching Unit